Guide to the Muslims in Brooklyn oral histories 2018.006
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Oral History Interview with Beatrice Sabir, August 28, 2018; 2018.006.29
  Beatrice Sabir was born in 1947 in Sumter, South Carolina. She moved to New York City as a young adult and joined the Nation of Islam in 1964. She worked in the Nation of Islam-affiliated Shabazz Restaurant in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan before opening Neighborhood Bakery with her husband in 1972 in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. The bakery's market grew to include contracts with correctional facilities; accounts with local grocery stores, delis, and restaurants; and catering for cultural events. She also served on the board of directors of Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah in Bedford-Stuyvesant.
  In this interview, Beatrice Sabir discusses her childhood in South Carolina and Boston. She speaks on her exposure to Islam as a child, joining the Nation of Islam as a young adult, and her memories of Black Family Day on Randall's Island in 1972. She expands on her ongoing involvement with Muhammad Mosque No. 7C (later known as Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah) in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, including participating in Muslim Girls Training - General Civilization Class (MGT-GCC) as a young woman. She also talks at length about opening Neighborhood Bakery with her husband, including the bakery's transition from retail to wholesale and its emphasis on the bean pie. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  African American cooking; African American Muslims -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bakeries -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Black Muslims -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Family-owned business enterprises -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Food -- Social aspects; Grocery trade -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islam -- Customs and practices; Martial arts -- Religious aspects -- Islam; Muslim converts -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Masjid Muhammad 7C (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Salima Malik Ahmed, August 30, 2018; 2018.006.30
  Salima Malik Ahmed was born in 1959 in Wah Cantonment, Pakistan. She worked as a teacher on a nearby Air Force base until marrying her husband in 1985. She immigrated to the United States shortly after their marriage, spending a few years in the Jackson Heights neighborhood of Queens before eventually settling in the Bensonhurst neighborhood of Brooklyn. She raised her children in the Ahmadiyya community centered around the nearby Masjid Bait ul Tahir, where she also taught religious classes.
  In this interview, Salima Malik Ahmed discusses growing up in Wah Cantonment, Pakistan, including her family, their Ahmadiyya Muslim faith, and her arranged marriage to her husband. She expands on their immigration to the United States, her memories of the Jackson Heights neighborhood of Queens, and raising her children in the Bensonhurst neighborhood of Brooklyn. She also speaks at length about her involvement with Masjid Bait Ul Tahir, an Ahmadiyya mosque in Bensonhurst. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  Bensonhurst (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Jackson Heights (New York, N.Y.); Queens (New York, N.Y.); Punjab (Pakistan); Ahmadiyya; Arranged marriage -- Pakistan; Child rearing -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- New York; Islam -- Customs and practices; Islam -- Prayers and devotions; Muslim families; Religion and culture -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Religious pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women in Islam -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Masjid Bait ul Tahir (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Rabia Ahsin, September 1, 2018; 2018.006.32
  Rabia Ahsin was born in 1991 in the Midwood neighborhood of Brooklyn. While studying political science at Brooklyn College as an undergraduate student, she joined the school's Islamic Society of Brooklyn College as well as with the Muslim Women's Educational Initiative, both of which were targeted by the New York City Police Department for religiously-motivated surveillance by an undercover officer while she was a member. She also became an outspoken activist against human rights abuses, including protesting with the school's newly-formed Students for Justice in Palestine and focusing her studies on surveillance in New York City. She went on to work as a special education teacher at all all girls' secondary school.
  In this interview, Rabia Ahsin discusses growing up in a Punjabi Muslim family in the Midwood and Ditmas Park neighborhoods of Brooklyn. She speaks extensively about the complex relationship between faith and culture, including her own connection to her Punjabi roots and her exploration of different traditions and customs within Islam. She expands on her education at Brooklyn College, including the hostility she experienced when she joined a school organization that advocated against violence in Palestine; studying human rights abuses against Muslims with Professor Jeanne Theoharis; and the undercover police officer who infiltrated the Islamic Society of Brooklyn College. She also talks about her struggles with mental health. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  Children of immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Clothing and dress -- Religious aspects -- Islam; Food -- Social aspects -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Hijab (Islamic clothing) -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islamophobia -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslim women -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Pakistanis -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Political activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women in Islam -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ditmas Park (New York, N.Y.); Midwood (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn College
- Oral History Interview with Mamnunul Haq, September 6, 2018; 2018.006.33
  Mamnunul Haq was born in 1962 in Sandwip, Bangladesh. He married his wife in 1988 and immigrated to the United States in 1991. He began driving a yellow medallion taxi in New York City in 1995 and was a strong advocate for taxi workers' rights, including co-founding the Bangladesh Yellow Society New York, the Bengal Cabbie Society, and the New York Taxi Driver's Alliance in in the mid-1990s. He retired from driving his taxi after a violent attack from a passenger left him hospitalized in 2005, and went on to become involved in health education and community organization in the Kensington neighborhood of Brooklyn, including supporting the local Avenue C Plaza and serving on a community board.
  In this interview, Mamnunul Haq discusses growing up in Sandwip, Bangladesh; his father's position in the local community; his political activism in Bangladesh; his marriage to his wife; and his immigration to the United States. He expands on his experiences driving a yellow medallion taxi in New York City, including his work to advocate for taxi drivers' rights and safety; co-founding the Bangladesh Yellow Society New York, the Bengal Cabbie Society, and the New York Taxi Driver's Alliance; and being seriously injured by a passenger. He also speaks at length about his memories of the East New York and Kensington neighborhoods of Brooklyn, especially regarding community organization in Kensington; serving on a community board; and his friendship with New York City council member Brad Lander. Interview conducted by Svetlana Kitto.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); East New York (New York, N.Y.); Kensington (New York, N.Y.); Sandwīp Island (Bangladesh); Bangladeshis; Community organization -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Education -- Bangladesh; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Labor policy -- New York (State); Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Muslim families -- Bangladesh; Political activists; Religious pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Ridesharing -- New York (State) -- New York; Taxicab drivers -- New York (State) -- New York; Taxicab industry -- New York (State) -- New York; Victims of violent crimes -- New York (State) -- New York; Lander, Brad
- Oral History Interview with Damirzhan and Aliakbar Azimov, September 10, 2018; 2018.006.34
  Damirzhan Azimov was born in 1974 near Taraz in the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (now Kazakhstan). He was a farmer before immigrating to the United States in 2011 with his son, Aliakbar, and the rest of their family. They settled in Brooklyn and he worked as a truck and paratransit driver before opening the Dungan cuisine-centered restaurant, Lagman House, in the Sheepshead Bay neighborhood of Brooklyn.
  Aliakbar Azimov was born in 1998 in Taraz, Kazakhstan. He immigrated to the United States in 2011 with his father, Damirzhan, and the rest of their family. He worked as a manager at his family's Dungan cuisine-centered restaurant, Lagman House, in the Sheepshead Bay neighborhood of Brooklyn while attending Stoney Brook University in Brookhaven, Long Island.
  In this interview, Damirzhan and his son Aliakbar discuss their family, especially regarding their Dungan ancestors' migration from China to escape persecution; Damirzhan's memories of living under the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (Soviet Union); and the cultural shifts they both observed following the establishment of the nation of Kazakhstan. They also speak at length about their family's immigration to the United States; settling in Brooklyn; and opening their Dungan cuisine-centered restaurant, Lagman House, in the Sheepshead Bay neighborhood of Brooklyn. Damirzhan's answers to interview questions were translated by Aliakbar. Interview conducted by Svetlana Kitto.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Sheepshead Bay (New York, N.Y.); Soviet Union; Taraz (Kazakhstan); Cooking, Hui -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Dungans; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islam -- Customs and practices; Racism -- Kazakhstan; Restaurants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Russian language
- Oral History Interview with Darlene Bashir, September 10, 2018; 2018.006.35
  Darlene Bashir was born in 1958 in New York City. She was raised by a Baptist family in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan and the Bedford-Stuyvesant and Brownsville neighborhoods of Brooklyn. She married her husband and embraced Islam in the mid-1970s. She earned a bachelor's degree from Baruch College and graduate degrees from Metropolitan College of New York and Adelphi University, all in Manhattan. She worked in the corporate world before entering the education field, becoming the director of the Clara Muhammad School of Masjid Khalifah in 1998.
  In this interview, Darlene Bashir discusses growing up in a racially mixed family in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan and the Brownsville neighborhood of Brooklyn, including her early experiences within the White Rock Baptist Church in Harlem; her education in primarily white schools; and meeting her first husband. She also speaks at length about her Muslim faith, especially regarding her early exploration of Islam, her admiration of Warith Deen Mohammed's teachings, and her experiences at Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. She expands on becoming the director of the Clara Muhammad School of Masjid Khalifah in 1998 and marrying Masjid Khalifah's imam, Rodney Adib Rashid (also interviewed for this collection), in 2006. In addition, she talks about raising her five children, losing one of them in infancy, and her work in the corporate world. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  African American Muslims -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Black Muslims -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Child rearing -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Death -- Religious aspects -- Islam; Interfaith families -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslim converts from Christianity -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Racially mixed families -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Racism in education -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Religious education of children -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brownsville (New York, N.Y.); Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Baseera Khan, September 11, 2018; 2018.006.36
  Baseera Khan was born in 1980 to Indian immigrants in Denton, Texas. She became involved in the arts as a young adult, earning a bachelor of the fine arts from the University of North Texas in Denton and a master of the fine arts from Cornell University in Ithaca, New York. Her artwork has often focused around the intersection of identity, politics, and culture. She participated in art shows and performances at various New York cultural institutions, and her solo exhibition, iamuslima, was first shown at the Participant Inc. Gallery in New York City and later had installments in Texas and Colorado. As a teacher, she also worked to create safe spaces for self-expression and encouraged others to think critically about how a creator's identities inform their work.
  In this interview, Baseera Khan discusses her parents' early lives in India, her experiences growing up in their insular immigrant family in Denton, Texas, and her encounters with bullying and racism from the broader Denton community. She talks extensively about her involvement in the arts and about "creating spaces" through her artwork, especially regarding her show iamuslima and the design class she was teaching at the New School's Parsons School of Design in New York City during the 2016 presidential election. Throughout the interview, she also repeatedly returns to her feminist interpretation of Islam; the intersection between prejudice, capitalism, and artistic expression; and her broader philosophy regarding the societal inequities around us. In addition, she talks about her formal education and studying art in school. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  American artists -- United States; Capitalism -- Moral and ethical aspects; Children of immigrants -- Texas -- Denton; Colorism -- Texas; Feminism -- Religious aspects -- Islam; Immigrants -- Texas -- Denton; Internet and activism; Islam and art -- United States; Islamophobia -- United States; Muslim artists -- United States; Patriarchy; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 2016; South Asian families -- Texas; South Asian Americans -- United States; Women artists -- United States; Women in Islam; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Denton (Tex.)
- Oral History Interview with Nailah Lymus, September 12, 2018; 2018.006.37
  Nailah Lymus was born in 1983 in Oneonta, New York. She was raised in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn. She used her experiences with her high school fashion club at Benjamin Banneker Academy for Community Development and internship at a local boutique, both in the Clinton Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn, to launch her clothing and accessory line 'Amirah Creations' in 2003. She founded Underwraps Modeling Agency in 2012 to represent female models who had strong religious or cultural convictions around modesty, and started the MODA MANTRA Magazine to feature modest fashion in 2017. She also served on Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah's board and taught at the mosque's Clara Muhammad School, which her son attended.
  In this interview, Nailah Lymus discusses growing up in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn, her family's interest in the fine arts, and her childhood experiences at Masjid At-Taqwa and Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah, both in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. She also speaks extensively about her lifelong interest in fashion that embraces religious modesty, including early experimentation with her own clothing and jewelry, involvement with her high school fashion club and internship at a nearby boutique, launching her clothing and accessory line 'Amirah Creations,' founding the Underwraps Modeling Agency, and starting MODA MANTRA Magazine. In addition, she expands on raising her son and her support for Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah, including serving on the mosque's board, teaching in their school, and participating in a youth outreach committee. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  African American Muslims -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Child rearing -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Clinton Hill (New York, N.Y.); Communities -- Religious aspects -- Muslims; Hijab (Islamic clothing) -- United States; Islamic religious education of children -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Modeling agencies; Modesty -- Religious aspects -- Islam; Muslim women -- Clothing -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women fashion designers -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women in Islam -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Masjid At-Taqwa (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Suheir Hammad, September 13, 2018; 2018.006.38
  Suheir Hammad was born in 1973 in Amman, Jordan. Her family immigrated to the United States in 1979 and settled in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. She started writing poetry as a teenager, often drawing from her family's history and her own experiences as a Palestinian Muslim woman in New York City. Her poetry collections Born Palestinian, Born Black and Drops of This Story were both published in 1996. She gained addition recognition with her poem "First Writing Since," which was centered around the September 11 Terrorist Attack in 2001, performing it for the pilot for the Peabody award-winning HBO show Russell Simmons presents Def Poetry and in the Tony award-winning Broadway play Russell Simmons Presents Def Poetry Jam on Broadway. She published additional collections of her poetry called ZaatarDiva in 2006 and Breaking Poems in 2008, as well as an updated version of Born Palestinian, Born Black in 2010. Her work has also been featured in various anthologies, magazines, plays, and films.
  In this interview, Suheir Hammad discusses her family's roots in Palestine; their displacement to Jordan in 1949; and her childhood in Brooklyn and Staten Island. She talks at length about social justice, including gender, privilege, prejudice, and violence in her community. She elaborates about her passion for hip-hop; spiritual and religious convictions; and development as a poet. She expands on her poem "First Writing Since," which centered around the September 11 Terrorist Attack in 2001, and her subsequent involvement in the Peabody award-winning HBO show Russell Simmons presents Def Poetry and in the Tony award-winning Broadway play Russell Simmons Presents Def Poetry Jam on Broadway. In addition, she touches on her religious and secular education. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  Hip-hop -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islam and the performing arts -- United States; Misogyny -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslim women authors -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Palestinian Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Poetry slams -- United States; Poets, Palestinian Arab -- United States; Privilege (Social psychology) -- New York (State) -- New York; Racism and the arts -- United States; Refugees, Palestinian Arab; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001, in literature; Social justice -- United States; Women -- Violence against -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women in Islam -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Simmons, Russell
- Oral History Interview with Fatima Shama, September 17, 2018; 2018.006.39
  Fatima Shama was born in 1973 in the Parkchester neighborhood of the Bronx. She earned a bachelor of the arts degree from the State University of New York at Binghamton and a master of public administration from Baruch College's School of Public Affairs Executive Program in New York City. After college, she worked with the Arab American Family Support Center and the Greater Brooklyn Health Coalition to improve New Yorkers' access to services like healthcare and education. She served in New York City Mayor Michael Bloomberg's administration from 2006-2014, first as Senior Education Policy Advisor and then as Commissioner of Immigrant Affairs. During her tenure, she worked to build stronger ties between Muslim communities and the city government. After leaving the administration, she became Executive Director of the Fresh Air Fund, a nonprofit organization focused on providing low-income children in New York City with access to nature.
  In this interview, Fatima Shama discusses her upbringing in the Parkchester neighborhood of the Bronx, especially regarding the emphasis her Catholic Brazilian mother and Muslim Palestinian father put on embracing her multicultural and interfaith roots. She expands on performing the traditional Palestinian 'dabke' folk dance with dance groups as a teenager, her religious and secular education, and her exploration of Islam through women scholars in college. She speaks about her commitment to activism to promote the rights of Muslim Americans, especially regarding her work with the Arab American Family Support Center and Muslims Against Terrorism. She also talks about her marriage and three children. Fatima Shama was also interviewed on October 2, 2018 for this collection. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Brazilians -- New York (State) -- New York; Children of immigrants -- New York (State) -- New York; Children of interfaith marriage -- New York (State) -- New York; Cultural pluralism -- New York (State) -- New York; Folk dancing, Arab -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- New York; Islam -- Customs and practices; Multiculturalism -- New York (State) -- New York; Muslim women -- New York (State) -- New York; Palestinian Arabs; Parkchester (New York, N.Y.); Religious education of children -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Social service -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); Women in Islam -- New York (State) -- New York; Arab American Family Support Center, Inc. (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Ahmed Nasser, September 18, 2018; 2018.006.40
  Ahmed Nasser was born in 1966 in the village of Almayanah in Yemen. He immigrated to the United States in 1986 and settled in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. He worked in family-owned restaurants and earned undergraduate degrees with New York City College of Technology in Brooklyn and Baruch College in Manhattan before joining the New York City Police Department (NYPD) in 2000. As a detective and member of the Community Affairs Bureau, he worked to improve communication between Muslim immigrant communities and the NYPD in the years following the September 11 Terrorist Attacks in 2001. He also cofounded the American Muslim Law Enforcement Officers Association in 2001 and the NYPD Muslim Officers Society in 2004.
  In this interview, Ahmed Nasser speaks extensively about his career as a Muslim detective in the New York City Police Department (NYPD), which he joined in 2000. He elaborates on his work to build relationships between law enforcement and Muslim immigrant communities across the city, especially following the September 11 Terrorist Attacks in 2001. In addition, he talks about educating his fellow police officers about Islam and his efforts to secure accommodations surrounding religious customs and practices for Muslims serving in the NYPD. He also touches on his family, immigration to the United States, and attachment to Brooklyn. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.